<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the King at White-hall on Tuesday, November the 5th, 1700 by William Fleetwood ...</title>
            <author>Fleetwood, William, 1656-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39746</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18777774</idno>
  <idno type="VID">108331</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248561208</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1258</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40234</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">18777774</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39746)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108331)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1653:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the King at White-hall on Tuesday, November the 5th, 1700 by William Fleetwood ...</title>
                  <author>Fleetwood, William, 1656-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Charles Harper ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by His Majesties special command."</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 29.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XXXIII, 15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108331:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the KING AT <hi>WHITE-HALL,</hi> ON <hi>Tuesday,</hi>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">November</hi> the 5th. 1700.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Fleetwood,</hi> Chaplain in Ordinary to His MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">Publish'd by His Majesties Special Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for CHARLES HARPER, at the <hi>Flower-de-Luce</hi> overagainst S. <hi>Dunstan</hi>'s Church, in <hi>Fleet-street.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:108331:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:108331:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd before the KING, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> Chap. xxiii. Vers. 15.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wo unto you Scribes and Pharisees, Hypocrites; for ye compass Sea and Land, to make One Prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyte; and when he is made, ye make him two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold more the Child of Hell than yourselves.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>OUR Saviour being sent of God, to reform the World in general, and in particular the great Corruptions that had over-spread the <hi>Jews</hi> his own People, both in their Practice and Opinion; found the greatest Opposition to his good Design, from the Scribes and Pharisees, who being in great Reputation with the common People, for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:108331:3"/> their most scrupulous precise observance of all the Traditions of the Elders, and a seeming Austerity of Life and Manners, led them wherever they pleased, and prejudiced them exceedingly against his Doctrine, and his Person. He therefore sets himself to undeceive these People, and let them know, what false and wicked Men these their Guides and Directors were, and how unworthy of their Admiration and Esteem: that they were not in the least, the Men they would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be; but endeavoured, in all their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to make a fine shew of Zeal and Holiness, without any Truth or Substance at the bottom; and cover'd very bad Designs under these Masques, and fair pretences. Upon this account it is, that in all his denunciations of Wo and Wrath, to the Scribes and Pharisees; he also adds, that they were <hi>Hypocrites.</hi> He says, <hi>They bound heavy burthens, and grievous to be born, on other peoples shoulders, but would not themselves move them with one of their fingers;</hi> laid heavy Penances on Others that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, and told them a world of things were absolutely necessary, but liv'd themselves at ease, free from that discipline: <hi>that all they did, was to be seen of Men,</hi> and to receive their Praise and Honour, living wholly to the World, and its Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plause and Interest, without any good Design, in any thing they undertook. Amongst other
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:108331:3"/> Reproofs, this of the Text is One; that the very Zeal which they shew'd in converting Gentiles to the Jewish Faith, was at the bottom stark naught, and tended only to the greater Mischief of those poor People who were converted by them. <hi>Wo unto you Scribes and Pharisees, Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites; for ye compass Sea and Land, to gain One Proselyte, and when he is made, ye make him two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold more the Child of Hell, than yourselves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words we will, <hi>First,</hi> Consider in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. <hi>Secondly,</hi> See, what Use we may make of them: And <hi>Lastly,</hi> Make what Application may be proper to this present Occasion.</p>
            <p>I. Of the words in themselves. <hi>To make a Proselyte,</hi> is to gain One over to our Party, or Opinion: and for a Jew to make a Proselyte, was, to convert a Gentile from his belief and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of many Gods, to the belief and worship of the One and only true God, and call'd by the <hi>Jews,</hi> the God of <hi>Israel.</hi> Some there were, who were thus converted, and went no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; others were perswaded to embrace the Jewish Faith, in all its Branches; to be circumcised, and to keep the whole Law of <hi>Moses,</hi> and to be made, thereby, partakers of all the Blessings promised by God to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Children. The first of these were indeed Proselytes to Sense and Reason, and returned to Natural Religion, rather than Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selytes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:108331:4"/> to the Jewish Faith, any farther than that the belief of One God was the Chief Article of it, and that a <hi>Jew</hi> became the happy Instrument of bringing them to Reason. It is therefore very probable, that the Proselytes of which our Saviour speaks in this place, were of the latter sort, such as were circumcised, and submitted to all the Law of <hi>Moses,</hi> and whatever else of Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, Customs and Traditions, were then held necessary at home, and preach'd abroad by these new Missionaries. <hi>To compass Sea and Land,</hi> is, to take great Pains, to labour hard, and go a great way, to undergo much Difficulty, and much Hazard, as they who make great Voyages by Sea, and Journeys by Land, are wont to do. <hi>To make One, twofold more a Child of Hell, than himself,</hi> is to leave him in a worse Condition than you found him, by a great deal: to make him wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keder, and consequently much more liable to Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment.</p>
            <p>We must see a little into the meaning of this. The bringing Gentiles from the worship of many Gods to the worship of One and the true One, was certainly a good Work, and therefore is not here condemn'd, we may be sure, by Christ; and the bringing them to the Jewish Faith, to the belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all that <hi>Moses</hi> and the Prophets had said, was still better; for thither our Saviour himself remits
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108331:4"/> the <hi>Jews,</hi> when they would know, <hi>who,</hi> and <hi>what</hi> he was, <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> saith he, <hi>for in them ye think ye have eternal Life, and they are they, which testifie of Me.</hi> This was the best prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they could make, to receive him as the <hi>Messiah,</hi> promised by God to the Fathers, and spoken of by <hi>Moses</hi> and the Prophets; here the particulars both of his Life and Death were to be found; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Account, the <hi>Jews</hi> who had these Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in their hands, and were oblig'd to read them carefully, are much more faulty in rejecting the <hi>Messiah,</hi> than others could be, who heard of no such Writings, nor receiv'd them as inspired Books; and therefore knew of no such Promises, or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, to be fulfill'd; the converting therefore of Gentiles to the belief of <hi>Moses</hi> and the Prophets, was the best disposition they could put them in, for entertaining the <hi>Messiah</hi> when they should see him coming: and therefore the Zeal of these Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting Missionaries, as far as it intended, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected this, was good, and was not condemn'd by Christ, we may be confident. And because the <hi>Jews</hi> were themselves circumcis'd by God's Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, and express Command, and could not otherwise be call'd <hi>Jews,</hi> nor enter into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God, nor be partakers of the Blessings, and peculiar Privileges, promis'd them, as such; 'tis very probable, they must induce the Converts
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108331:5"/> they intended to make, that they might be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the same Promises, to enter into the same Covenant, by the same way, the <hi>Jews</hi> did, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by being Circumcised; and consequently they must become <hi>Debtors to the whole Law,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form exactly to all its Rites and Ceremonies, as the Original <hi>Jews</hi> did. Nor does there appear any thing blame-worthy in all this; for besides that, Christ himself submitted to Circumcision, and observ'd the Law of <hi>Moses,</hi> we find not any where, that he condemn'd any One, for doing the like. And tho' he intended to abrogate that ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiating Sacrament, and all the Ceremonial Law of <hi>Moses,</hi> in its proper time, and might therefore think such Conversions to Judaism at such a time, and so near the Period he would put to it, not very seasonable or necessary; yet 'tis not to be thought, he would condemn with such severity and sharpness, the Zeal of such as should attempt to convert the Gentiles to perfect Judaism, which <hi>they</hi> thought necessary, and he himself had not as yet declar'd against, or disapproved.</p>
            <p>Since, then, the Scribes and Pharisees, were not themselves the Children of Hell, for their being <hi>Jews,</hi> and for believing <hi>Moses</hi> and the Prophets, submitting to Circumcision, and observing the whole Law; we are not to think, their Prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes and Converts, became Children of Hell,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108331:5"/> by becoming <hi>Jews,</hi> and much less doubly so, and worse than their Converters. But we must needs remember, that the Scribes and Pharisees, are eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where represented by Christ, as the great Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupters of the Jewish Faith. They had so gloss'd, and commented upon the Scriptures, that Truth was obscur'd and lost under them: they had so darkned Prophecies, that they had wholly laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side the expectation of their Completion, at their proper times and seasons, or applied them so to other matters, that the People were diverted to Objects, they had nothing to do with, and could not look to the things that most concern'd them: they had superinduc'd such a world of Rites and Ceremonies, to those that <hi>Moses</hi> had commanded them, (which one would have thought had been enow) that <hi>Moses</hi> would himself have hardly known his own Institution; and they were into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerably troublesome by a most fanciful signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cance, and became through weakness and super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitious fear, so necessary in the most common Actions of Life, that they were look'd upon as parts of their Religion; and Men became de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil'd and abominable by Neglect of them, and pure and holy by a nice Observance of them: they had made such an Exposition on the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, that a Man might almost keep every one of them in breaking them. Our Saviour tells
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:108331:6"/> them, they had made <hi>them of none effect, through their traditions:</hi> and a great part of his Business was, to bring them again to their Old Sense and Signification; his Sermons were divided betwixt <hi>Ye have heard of old,</hi> and — <hi>but I say unto you</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise.</p>
            <p>In a Word, The Corruptions that reigned, and had done so a great while before, amongst the <hi>Jews,</hi> were incredibly great, and most de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable. And, in truth, their Practice went hand in hand with them; their Doctrines were exactly calculated for Ease and Liberty, and for Indulgence to Vice and all Enormities. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour hated Sin, with the most mortal Hatred, because he knew the Mischief that it did to those he loved, and knew what it, at length, would cost him; but never did a holy Prophet treat Sinners with more Mildness, Pity, and Good-Nature, with less Upbraidings and Reproaches, than he, where he discern'd the least Relenting, Tenderness, or Inclination to Goodness. And therefore, one may easily believe, That where he is moved to speak the sharpest and severest things, and to denounce such Wo and Wrath, there was the greatest Cause, and justest Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation for it, that could be; and therefore we may well conclude, the Scribes and Pharisees were certainly the worst and wickedest of Men.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108331:6"/> This we may take for granted, because the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels are so full of it.</p>
            <p>But what is the Connexion betwixt <hi>their</hi> being so wicked, and their <hi>Proselytes</hi> being as bad, or much worse? with some Probality this, — that they who were themselves so tainted and corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both in Principles and Practice, would infuse the same corrupt Principles into their Disciples, and form them to the same Practice with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. They would deliver them the Law of <hi>Moses,</hi> the Lessons of the Prophets, and the Sum of the <hi>Jewish</hi> Faith, as they themselves had learnt it, with all the false Glosses, trifling Comments, unwarrantable Additions, wicked Distinctions, Relaxations, Dispensations of Duty, Commutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for Neglect; and, in a Word, with the whole corrupted Mass of their Traditions; which made the Jewish Church, at this Time, such an Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to Christ. There was all the Likelihood in the World, that People so very loose and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, would propagate their Errors and Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and the Disciples then must needs be as wicked as their Masters.</p>
            <p>To say the Proselytes would be <hi>twofold more the Children of Hell,</hi> than they who made them Proselytes, is an exaggerating Speech, and rather condemns the Masters than the Scholars: They who pretended so much Zeal, would teach the Gentiles such a Doctrine as would leave them
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108331:7"/> worse than it found them; it would pervert their very natural Principles: and that which true Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son would instruct them in, and urge them to do, would be defeated by Traditions of their Masters, and false Expositions of Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which came indeed from God.</p>
            <p>I will give an Instance or two of this, because it is of Moment. We are made by God, by stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in need of one anothers Assistance, to love one another, and to do each other all good Offices, in this we are instructed by the Light of Nature, and when we are secure our selves, we need no Command of God, to carry us to the helping o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in Distress; we do it of our own accord, and condemn our selves in the Neglect of it, if we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make some good Excuse. This natural Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation the <hi>Jews</hi> deliver'd themselves from, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding some Commands of God, which for bad them closer Commerce than ordinary with idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Nations, for fear of being infected with their abominable Practices, to such a rigorous and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable Extremity of keeping Distance, that they would not so much as do the common Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Humanity to any but <hi>Jews;</hi> they would see a Heathen perish for want of necessaries, rather than supply him with them; they would not so much as look kindly, nor speak a good word, much less bestow a Benefit on any one but <hi>Jews.</hi> They were remarkable for their morose, and sullen, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:108331:7"/> ill-natur'd Manners, and were equally hated and despised by all the World that knew them. This was not owing to Nature nor to Gods Commands, if rightly understood, but to a false and corrupt Exposition of them, begun in Error, and continu'd on by naughty Custom, and became in time a venerable Tradition.</p>
            <p>That which follows is much worse. The Light of Nature teaches all the World, without a posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Command of God, to succour and support our Parents in Necessity, whether driven to it by Age, Infirmities, by Losses or Misfortunes; 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly our common Duty to do it, and nothing can dispense with it, according to our Abilities: but the <hi>Jews</hi> determin'd, that if a Man had devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Estate to the Use of the Temple, or any part of Gods Service, he was then acquitted of his Duty to his Parents: and if they came to him in never so great Distress, and begg'd his Help, he might answer them, No, <hi>it is Corban,</hi> that Estate with which I might have profited you, is dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted now to God by Vow, and I can do you no farther Service. <hi>Thus,</hi> saith our Lord, <hi>have ye made the Commands of God, of no effect</hi> or Obligation, <hi>by your Traditions.</hi> These are plain Instances how the Light of Nature may be extinguish'd by preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Revelation: and as plain Proofs that such a reveal'd Religion (<hi>i. e.</hi> corrupted so) is worse than <hi>Gentilism;</hi> corrupting their natural Notions of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:108331:8"/> Good and Evil, and putting them on Practices, that Reason, whilst untainted, would abhor.</p>
            <p>But if these words are to be understood exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Letter, that the Proselytes would become much worse than they who gain'd them over, (of which I think there is no necessity) then we may say, that so our Saviour saw it would actually be, tho' he assign'd no reason why it would be so: but this we also may ourselves observe, that so it sometimes happens, that People exceed their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and Corrupters, in their own wicked way; and out-do their Originals, becoming themselves Examples, and great Models of Perfection, in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and sinful Practices. But as it is easier much, so it is more probable, to think, our Saviour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, by this severe and angry Scheme of Speech, to say the Scribes and Pharisees, notwithstanding all their Zeal for Conversion of Gentiles, had better have let them alone, for that, being them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves so abominably Corrupt, they could not but make their Proselytes more wicked than they found them, and as bad as themselves, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently make them liable to greater Wrath and Punishment, than they had been, had they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in their Ignorance and Darkness.</p>
            <p>II. Let us see, in the second place, what Use we may make of these Matters. And that will be, at this time, to observe these Two things: <hi>First,</hi> That wicked Men may be as full of Zeal, as good
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108331:8"/> ones, to propagate their Errors and Corruptions. And <hi>Secondly,</hi> That therefore Zeal is not of it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to be regarded, but with Respect to the <hi>End</hi> it aims at, the <hi>Means</hi> it uses to accomplish the End, and the <hi>Effect</hi> that is like to follow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Wicked Men may be as full of Zeal, as good Ones, to propagate their Errors and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions. These Scribes and Pharisees so often call'd upon by Christ (and always for their Faults) were full of Zeal, for converting Gentiles; and this is the more observable, in that there is no Command in all the Jewish Law, obliging the <hi>Jews</hi> to labour for the Conversion of the Gentiles, a certain Sign, this Law was not intended to be the standing Rule, and the Religion of the whole World. There is indeed provision made in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral places of the Law, how to receive and use <hi>Strangers,</hi> in case they were willing to become <hi>Jews;</hi> and in the 60<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>Isaiah,</hi> there is a large Prophecy, that Kings, and Nations, and many People should be gather'd to them; which may partly be applied to the Jewish State, before Christ's coming, tho' much more properly and truly to the Church of Christ. But there was no Command of God to set the <hi>Jews</hi> upon this Work of gaining them: and therefore the Zeal of doing it was so much greater, in being voluntary; and moreover, this their Zeal was accompanied with many Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties and Hazards, it cost them. Time, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108331:9"/> Pains, and much Money; such Undertakings re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire them all; <hi>they compass Sea and Land to gain a Proselyte.</hi> No dangers frightned them, they left their Native Country, their Parents and Relations, their Ease, Estate, and all Conveniencies of Life, to enter on a strange Climate, unusual Diet, and a new way of living; they ventur'd on unknown Countries, People of a new Tongue, new Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoms, and new Manners; and it may be where there were inhospitable Laws, and rigorous Edicts against Foreigners, and Death itself denounc'd to such as would dare to decry the Religion, Gods, and Worship of the Country, and introduce a new Superstition; but neither the Storms and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pests in their Passage, nor Death in all its frightful Shapes at Sea, nor all the Hazards of their Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Continuing in a strange Country, could hinder them from coming to Convert them: No Considerations could abate their Zeal: the desire they had of doing them the greatest Good imaginable, carried it above their Security and Self-Love, and private Interest, and all their Fears of Death and Danger.</p>
            <p>Here is One among us that pretends to preach up Reformation, and exclaims upon the great Corruption of Faith and Manners that prevails a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, and especially his Superiours, the Scribes, and Pharisees, and Elders: He pretends above all others, that his sole Aim is the Glory of God,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:108331:9"/> and the good of Mankind: but, do the Pains he takes, the Hardships he sustains, his tedious Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyings by Land, or his perilous Voyages by Sea, do these give Testimony to his Zeal and good Designs? Are these like the laborious and hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous Undertakings of the Scribes and Pharisees, who compass Sea and Land to make a Proselyte, who think that all is well bestowed, if they can gather up but one poor straying Sheep into the Fold of God's Church?</p>
            <p>This was the Zeal of those, against whom the Wo in the Text is denounced: they were, with all this Zeal, most wicked and corrupt People; and, I think, I need not spend time, in shewing that Zeal is common to all Men, of all Parties and Conditions, and is never, in itself, a Token of either a good or a bad Man, or of a good or bad Cause, or Design; it is a natural servour and warmth of Temper, rais'd higher than ordinary by some particular Considerations; and apt to be so rais'd, by that readiness the Spirits and Blood are always in, to motion. And it has always been observ'd, that the worst Causes and Designs, have been pursued with the greatest degrees of Zeal, by the worst of Men: Whether it be, that good Men trust too far to the Truth and Justice of good Causes, believing their natural Force and Power to be much greater than they are; or that they think they are so much the Care and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108331:10"/> of God's Providence, that they may slacken their own diligence, and leave it to him to secure, who loves their Cause, and is very able to look after it, and very much obliged, they think, in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice and Honour, to do it. Whatever it be that occasions it, 'tis commonly enough seen, that good People fall into Languors, Lukewarmness, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference; and prosecute a good and righteous Cause, with more Remissness, and less Zeal, than is truly reasonable, or than becomes them: and that wicked People pursue their unjust Designs, and corrupt Interests, with such intention of Zeal, such Application, Diligence, and earnest Solicitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that nothing can stand before them. Zeal therefore, of itself, tho' never so painful and labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and running never so great Hazards, is not to be regarded.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>in the Second place,</hi> Respect must needs be had to the <hi>End</hi> it proposes, the <hi>Means</hi> it pitches on, and the <hi>Effect</hi> that is like to follow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> We must look to the <hi>End</hi> that Zeal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses, whether it be good, or bad, or mixt: the Pretence may be God's Glory, and the Salvation of Souls, the bringing People to the knowledge of the Truth, and the correcting their bad Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; this is an Excellent and Noble End, and worthy of all the Zeal, and Pains, and Hazard, that a Man can take, and run; but this must be well look'd into, for this is generally pretended
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:108331:10"/> to by all Undertakers of Conversion, and makes their way clear before them; and there is no doubt but the Scribes and Pharisees recommended themselves to their intended Proselytes by these Pretences, when yet, it we believe our Saviour, they thought of nothing less: They had other purposes, and were excited by other Motives, than God's Glory, and the good of Souls; they had their own Interest, and Vain glory, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Parties. <hi>I seek not yours, but you,</hi> saith St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> But there are Missionaries, of another mind, that seek not Souls, but Gain, or Men for their Estates sake, and this is always to be well consider'd. Look well about, what sort of Countries these great Zealots chuse for Conquests, if it be <hi>Tyre,</hi> or <hi>Sidon,</hi> or <hi>Damascus,</hi> rich and trading Cities, or some ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure, and poor, tho' populous In land places; and to what sort of People they apply themselves, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the noble, generous, and wealthy, or to the poor and meaner ones. Mark if their Children flock to <hi>Swedeland, Denmark, Norway, Lapland, Russia,</hi> or to the poorer quarters of <hi>America,</hi> with so much hast, and in such Numbers, as to <hi>Mexico, Peru,</hi> the <hi>Eastern In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> and to <hi>England.</hi> See if the Glory of God, and good of Souls, make so much noise in the cold and barren <hi>North,</hi> as they do in warmer richer Climats, where <hi>Men</hi> reward as well as <hi>God,</hi> and yet where Souls are full as valuable, and dear to Him, as <hi>in the Land of</hi> Havilah, <hi>where there is Gold, and Bdellium, and the Onyx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone.</hi> Look therefore well to this, before you so com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:108331:11"/> the Zeal of those who compass Sea and Land, to make a Proselyte; see if there be no Interest at the bottom.</p>
            <p>Another End that Men may have and serve by these Conversions, is Vain-glory, the pride and pleasure of being thought, and reported, so zealous of propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Conversion of the World. It is not to be thought, without searching carefully into the bottom of one's own heart, and observing narrowly the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Practices of other People, what strange and difficult things, a Man's Vain-glory, and thirst of Fame and Commendation will put him upon, and make him undergo; what Pains and Labour he will be at, what Hardships he will sustain, for the reward of empty Praise and Admiration: the Glory of excelling other People, of being eminently singular, and distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishing ones self from the common Mass, hath occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion'd Men to run a thousand hazards, both at Sea and Land, to do a thousand wonders, and has written at least a hundred thousand Books. Let us make good use of every thing we can, but this light Fancy, is a great ingredient in almost every human Composition. When we go to reason, and think in earnest, we can hardly have the confidence to charge any one, that he takes great pains and runs great hazard, to satisfy his Vain glory, and to obtain the Praise of doing some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that other People do not, without intending any other better end: when yet, if the Man would speak his mind freely, this principle is surely at the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:108331:11"/> bottom. I make no other use of this sad Truth, at this time, than to suppose that Men may be stirr'd, even to undertake the best Designs, by the desire of Praise and Glory, Approbation and Esteem, and to be thought so zealous of God's honour and Man's good, as to venture Life and Liberty to promote 'em, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intending them in earnest. I see no reason to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude better of the Missionaries concern'd in the Text, their whole design being to make a good Appearance, and to shew well to the World, and to be praised of Men: and the taking so much Pains, and running so much Hazard, by compassing Sea and Land to make a Proselyte, was as likely to make a shew of true Zeal, and gain them the Admiration of the World, as any thing else, those things being the <hi>Tokens,</hi> that Men are truly in earnest.</p>
            <p>The making Parties, is also another End, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signing People may possibly aim at, even in making Converts; this indeed does usually follow, whether Men design it or no, the Proselytes do generally ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to their Converters Interest and Party, with great Good-will, with the utmost Zeal and Pertinacity; and are evermore the warmest in defending their New Choice, and in promoting it, and in with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, and bearing down all its Opposers. This was found true in the Apostles days; and <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> complains of it in his; and all Men have observ'd that the new Converts are still the forwardest, and most presumptuous, flaming with Zeal, as if they were to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:108331:12"/> redeem the time of their Ignorance past, make an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement for their former opposition, or neglect of Truth, and by something extraordinary, convince the World of the sincerity and earnest of their Conversion, making such quick advances, and such forward paces, that they may never think of cooling and retiring. This temper is exceeding fit for Parties, and a rare Spirit, for pursuing worldly Interests: and therefore they who have designs of such a sort, to serve, cannot do better than to make as many Proselytes as they can to their Religion, who are thereby engag'd most deeply in their Interests.</p>
            <p>Next to the <hi>End</hi> of Zeal, we are to consider the <hi>Means</hi> it uses to attain it: For true Religion will not be beholden to Evil, to obtain the good it aims at; it acts most uniformly with itself, and pitches upon means exactly just and honest; it pretends not to sanctify, by using them, means that are in themselves unhallowed and abominable; but takes the courses that are before acknowledg'd to be just, and reasonable and lawful, to compass its end by. If the Glory of God and the good of Souls, be the true end of those who would convert, and make Proselytes; the means must not be such as would dishonour God, and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice a Soul, disinteress'd and reasonable, against them. There must be nothing of falshood, cruelty, impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or impiety in them; for each of them are unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of God, and unbecoming a good Religion. There must be nothing contrary to our natural Notices; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:108331:12"/> contrary to our Senses; nothing contrary to the common Notions all Men have of good and evil. Whoever, in a word, to bring a Man to his Religion, will use such means as that Religion does itself abhor and forbid, is not acted, certainly by the true Spirit of that Religion, but by mistaken Zeal, at least, if not some worse Principle. But because a Man, before he be a Proselyte, will hardly understand thorowly what that Religion forbids, or admits of, he will be safe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in rejecting that Religion, that countenances Falshood, Inhumanity, impure Practices, or any thing that stands condemn'd by the Light of Nature, and the common Reason of Mankind.</p>
            <p>And so, one may say, <hi>in the last place,</hi> if the easie, natural, or common <hi>Effects</hi> of the Principles of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion be like to be dishonourable to God, and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of so good a name, we may conclude against it, and condemn the Zeal that would promote it. For true Religion never can, in itself, or just Consequence, either dishonour God, or do Mischief to Mankind.</p>
            <p>In passing our Judgment therefore upon Zeal, we must not barely regard the Pains it takes, nor the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards it runs, in Compassing Sea and Land to make Proselytes, but seriously respect the <hi>End</hi> it truly aims at (not what it pretends) the <hi>Means</hi> it uses to compass that End by, and the Effects that are likely to follow. All these things must be consider'd, when we would understand, whether the Zeal of making Proselytes, be truly good and laudable; for if either the <hi>End</hi> be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:108331:13"/> naught, or the <hi>Means</hi> unlawful, or the natural <hi>Effects</hi> of such Conversion, be the Corruption of good Manners, the Pains and Labours of these Missionaries, and the Hazards they run, are no good Arguments in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half. For the Scribes and Pharisees took all these pains, and ventur'd all these Hazards, and yet were <hi>Hypocrites: they compass'd Sea and Land, to make a Proselyte,</hi> and all they did by it, was, that they made him worse than he was before, and worse, if it could be, <hi>than Themselves.</hi> This is the Use we may make, at this time, of these Words of Christ.</p>
            <p>III. The Application of what has been said, to the Occasion of our present Meeting, may be this. We are to give God Thanks for the Deliverance of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on heretofore, from the Contrivance and Design of wicked Papists, to murder King and Prince, Bishops and Judges, Lords and Commons, met in Parliament, all at one Blow. A Work of the most devilish and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate Malice, quickest Execution, and most dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Consequence, that can be thought upon. And, in the next place, to give God Thanks for a Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Nation, of a fresher Date, from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs of the same Party, to destroy the Established Church, (for they pretended Kindness to <hi>the rest,</hi> and they believ'd them) to overturn our Laws, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern by a Force that we were Strangers to. Of these two Deliverances, the First was <hi>accomplish'd</hi> on this Day, by the Discovery of the <hi>Powder Plot.</hi> The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond was <hi>begun</hi> by the King's Arrival on our Shoars,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:108331:13"/> in order to preserve our Church, to settle and confirm our Laws, and to have us govern'd by them. These two Deliverances happening on the same day, we are to give God Thanks for both of 'em at the same time. Now both these dangerous Seasons, and all that came between them, were entirely owing to that intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, restless Zeal for Our Conversion, with which these Children of the Scribes and Pharisees, incessantly persue us; and for which they compass Sea and Land. And since there is no Plea, that sooner makes them way, and gains them▪ a more favourable Admission, nothing that prepossesses Peoples Minds with kinder Prejudice, than seeing the Voyages and Journeys that they take from forein Countries, their Perils by Water, and Perils by Land, their Perils from Strangers, and Perils from their own Countrymen, from Clamour, and Ill-will, and Penal Laws, and all to gain a Soul to God, and the true Religion; I thought it not amiss, to shew you, what a Zeal the Scribes and Pharisees had to make Proselytes, in the like manner, and what Pains they also took to compass Sea and Land, for the same Purpose, and yet were Hypocrites themselves, and Corrupters of those they would convert; and that therefore Zeal alone was not to be regarded, without the Consideration of the End, the Means, and probable Effects of such Conversion. Let us, to save a little time, suppose these Emissaries, who are, in proper time and place, as sharp and avaricious as the <hi>Jews,</hi> or <hi>Banian</hi> Merchants, the Masters of Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:108331:14"/> Turbulence, and Faction, and the greatest Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admirers in the World; let us suppose them, for once, to be, with respect to us, the most dis-interess'd, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>designing, open, modest, humble Men, that can be; and to have no other Aim or End, than the Glory of God, and the Salvation of <hi>English Souls:</hi> yet, what shall we do to justifie the <hi>Means</hi> they take to compass this End by? Will the Good <hi>End</hi> sanctifie Falshood, Villany, and Treachery, the destruction of all our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Civil Rights, the Overthrow of all our Laws, and the delivering us up a Prey to the Insolence of arbitrary Power? And if this cannot be brought about by civil means, by artful Management, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of Persuasion; will it justify such wicked Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and such inhumane Cruelties, as were design'd this day, to put an End to so many great and precious Lives, among us? Was this the way to save the <hi>Souls</hi> of those intended Victimes? Had they been purify'd by this strange Fire, and fitted for the Mercies of the Almighty? The <hi>End,</hi> I doubt, must be forgotten here, and this must be their way to bring their <hi>Children</hi> unto God, however ill it go with the poor Parents. But will the Children be inclin'd to think these means are proper for Conversion, and for begetting a good O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion in them of the Religion to which they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited? What sort of God is it, that is delighted with these humane Sacrifices? Does such a sanguinary Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin suit with Christ, who claims from God his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and from a soft and tender Virgin-Mother? Will
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:108331:14"/> Children be induc'd to leave the merciful good Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Natural Religion, for these most violent and brutal ones of a pretended Revelation? Can these a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable Cruelties make any other Impressions on the Standers by, than those of Hatred and Abhorrence, and a Resolution of flying from them as soon as pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly they can? The <hi>Nero's</hi> and the <hi>Maximins,</hi> the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cii</hi> and the <hi>Dioclesians</hi> thought this Way, and took these Methods to extirpate Christ's Religion; they were most happily mistaken. But who would think, that <hi>Christians,</hi> knowing this should fall in with the same courses, with just the contrary Design? Who would suspect Religion should be planted, settled, and confirm'd by Violence, by its great Friends, when its great Enemies use the same, to root it up, and destroy it? And yet we may defy the whole World to give us an Example, (one Example) where <hi>Popery</hi> could, with its own security, have ruin'd and destroy'd such as would not submit themselves to it, and did not. <hi>Popery</hi> is really an Usurpation on Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity, and like Usurpers, lives within its Guards, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisitors and Dragoons; it settles and supports itself, by Gibbets, Axes, Halters, by Fire and Sword, and all the Instruments of Death, and cruel Executions. As I know there is no Encouragement to these Proceedings, from <hi>Christs Religion,</hi> so I would only ask them Reparations for the great Scandal and Dishonours they do hereby to <hi>Natural Religion,</hi> and to the common Principles of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and pure Humanity.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:108331:15"/>
            <p>Let us see, <hi>in the last place,</hi> if the <hi>Effects</hi> be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable to the <hi>Pains</hi> that are taken, for our Conversion, when they take Place. How is the matter mended with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>? How is the Glory of God promoted, or the Good of Mankind, or the Salvation of Souls further'd? Do they tell us any thing of God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghost, that is contain'd in the Scriptures, which we did not believe before? Have they one Article of Faith, of Christs making, that we receive not equally with them? Or, in the point of Duty and good Morals, is there one Command of Christ that he enjoyns to do, but we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg we should do it; or one thing he prohibits us, but what we own we should abstain from? To what new Rule must we submit and turn? If that be not true Christianity, to believe all that our Lord enjoyns us to believe, either by himself or his Apostles, to do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he commands, and to omit whatever he prohibits, to make the Word of God the Rule of Faith and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to live in Union and Communion with our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors, Bishops, Priests and Deacons, rightly ordain'd, (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by our Adversaries themselves at first, if that will please) and in Love and Charity with one another; if this be not true Christianity, and indeed enough, where are we like to learn what is? and if it be, to what are we converted but to <hi>Party?</hi> Is God more honour'd by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Saints and Angels, than to him alone? Do we much glorifie our Lord, by making a thousand Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of Intercession for us, as well as He? Do we Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and much Pleasure to a Jealous God, to pray to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:108331:15"/> any of his Servants, for the same Favours and like Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that we ask of him? Does he regard us more for kneeling down and offering up our Prayers, not to say Incense, before an Idol or an Image? Does he delight ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to hear his People pray in an unknown Tongue, than with their Understanding? Or is he better pleased with the retrenching of the Cup, than with his own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution? I have neither Mind nor Leisure to speak to the Particulars in which we differ, the Diminutions and the Additions they have made <hi>from</hi> and <hi>to</hi> Christs Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, in both which true <hi>Popery</hi> consists. It is only to my present Purpose, to say, that there is not one point of true <hi>Popery,</hi> that can make a Man a truer Believer, or a better Man, than he was before, in our Communion. And therefore, to what are <hi>we</hi> to be converted? What have we to believe, or what to practice, but what we own our selves obliged to do before.</p>
            <p>How long then, shall we bear these Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risees among us, that are not only unnecessary, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious to us? One would have thought, that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance of this Day had so justly provok'd our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors, that they would never more have suffered such In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>endiaries amongst us; but have executed constantly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Laws they had justly made against them. 'Tis bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er indeed to repent of Mercy shewn, than of Severity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut 'tis not good to repent of <hi>that</hi> too often: Instead of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uiet and security gain'd by this Relaxation and Remis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>on of <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> the Nation gave this Faction Breath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd new Spirit. Unseasonable Condescensions do some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:108331:16"/> provoke to greater Insolence; and Mercy ill di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spleased, <hi>i. e.</hi> to vile ungenerous Spirits, is look'd upon as Fear, and encourages to bolder Undertakings. 'Tis now some 95 Years since this Conspiracy was to have taken place, yet from that Day to this, they have not lost a foot of Ground among Us in their general Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest; yet from that Day to this, they have been digging down our Walls and Fences, and undermining our Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; contriving the Destruction both of Church and State. The Nation was delivered on the 5<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> and on the 6<hi>th.</hi> we may well presume they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan again to carry on the same Design of ruining our Peace, by other Methods, which they have pursued, even to this Day. Our Histories, and our Memories, are full of the Disturbance they have given us; they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed, no less than all they could, to the Misfortune both of Prince and People; they occasion'd a world of troubles to One, and terribly embroyl'd Another, and to a Third, their Kindness, Favour, and Assistance were as fatal, as their Malice, and Opposition could have been, had they carried them never so high. Then did this lucky Day shine bright again, and brought a new Deliverance to the Nation; but, would they make it only a Deliverance from a present Storm of Violence, that was ready to pour upon us? Our Enemies live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and are mighty, it thunder'd for a Day or two, and they were frightned, and retir'd into their dark Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesses, but when the noise was over, they return'd again to their old Business, our Conversion; and have since that,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:108331:16"/> been busie at it, in despite of all our Laws and Statutes; we are indeed delivered from their open insults, we would be also from their secret underminings, from their seduction of our People, their <hi>leading captive silly Women, and such as are laden with divers lusts.</hi> What do they here, in a place, where they acknowledge no King, no Church, no Christians, but themselves and Party, unless it be to give us all these things, they think we want? Why do they haunt our Sick, frequent our Prisons, and creep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Peoples Houses, raise false Reports, detract from our Advantages, exaggerate our Misfortunes, and reproach our Government? In a word, to compleat our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, we would intreat those Sons of Zeal, to return a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain unto their Holy City, and both for ours, and for their own sake, to spare their painful Compassings of Sea and Land, to gain a Proselyte, since they make him, thereby, a worse Christian, and a worse Subject, than they found him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>A Sermon preach'd <hi>August</hi> the 4<hi>th.</hi> 1700. [on occasion of the Death of his Highness the Duke of <hi>Gloucester.</hi>] By Mr. <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> Printed for <hi>C. Harper.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>